Guide to the Cornell University English Department records, 1891-1987.
Cornell University English Department records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Cornell University English Department records, 1891-1987.
14-12-1227
Cornell University. English Department.
1 cubic ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts, publications
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Records documenting the administration of the Cornell English Department.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Records include office, committee, and personnel files; memos; student records; examinations, including an 1891 entrance examination; English scholarship and fellowship materials including lists of winners; selected records of the Freshman Humanities Program; correspondence; pamphlets; minutes of faculty meetings (1946-1957); and records of the department chairman, 1948-1968.
English Dept. lectures presented Monday, January 29, 2007 at Hollis E. Cornell Auditorium, Goldwin Smith Hall, Cornell University: Sandra M. Gilbert, "Finding Atlantis: Thirty Years of Exploring Women's Literary Traditions" and M.H. Abrams, "On Reading Poetry Aloud."
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell University.; Abrams, M. H. (Meyer Howard), 1912-2015.; Gilbert, Sandra M.; Cornell University -- Entrance requirements -- English.; Cornell University -- Examinations -- English.; Cornell University -- Funds and scholarships.; Cornell University -- Prizes.; Cornell University -- Students.; Cornell University; Cornell University. Freshman Humanities Program.; Cornell University. English Department
Subjects:
Feminism and literature.; Oral interpretation of poetry.; Examinations -- English; Feminism and literature; Oral interpretation of poetry; Scholarships; Students; Women and literature
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Departmental records are restricted to permission of office of origin.
CONTAINER LIST
- English Dept. lectures, January 29, 2007; 522 (Box DVD 2)
  Presented Monday, January 29, 2007 at Hollis E. Cornell Auditorium, Goldwin Smith Hall, Cornell University: Sandra M. Gilbert, "Finding Atlantis: Thirty Years of Exploring Women's Literary Traditions" and M.H. Abrams, "On Reading Poetry Aloud."
- Minutes of the Meetings of the Department of English, April 26, 1946 - November 12, 1957 (Box 1, Volume 1)
- Entrance Exam, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Exams, 1899-1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Exams, 1905-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Exams, 1910-1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Intra-departmental Memos, 1953-1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Administrative Correspondence, 1941-1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Faculty Biographical Information, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- List of Instructors, 1940-1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Memos Concerning the Medical Insurance Program at Cornell, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Reading Lists, 1949-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Lists of Graduate Students, 1937-1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Lists of Ph.Ds. and Dissertation Topics, 1938, 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Plagiarism, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Reading Lists for Honors Program, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Honors Program Committee Reports, undated, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Honors Program Correspondence, 1949-1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Honors Program Exams, 1948, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Honors Program Seminars, Lists of Students in Honors Program, undated, 1947-1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Honors Program Memos, 1941-1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Fellowships and Scholarships, 1949-1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Martin Sampson Fellowship, 1943-1956 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Fellowships, 1945, 1950, 1953, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Cornell - Glasgow Exchange Fellowship, Woodrow Wilson Fellowship, Post War Fellowships in Humanities
- Fellowship and Scholarships, 1950, 1952, 1953, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Faculty Fellowships (Ford Foundation), Olmstead Scholarship, Class of 1916 Fellowship
- Fellowships and Scholarships Lists of Elected, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Graduate Program Faculty Meetings, Memos About Reform, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Prizes, undated, 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Coit Tyler, Jo Stafford, Martin Wright, Morrison Poetry Price, Rogers Peet Advertising Prize.
- Prizes, 1943-1956 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Manuscript Club Contest, Guilford Essay Prize, Folder Library Prize, Cornell Dramatic Club Playwriting, Corson Browning Prize, Bess Berlow Cohan.
- Prize Information, 1943-1956 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Examanations - Masters and Ph.D. degrees, 1939-1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Schedule of Exams, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Examination Notices, Lists of Seminars, 1946-1956 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Examination Reading Lists, undated, 1948, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Committee Files, 1936-1938, 1953, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Arts Festival, Fellowship, Committee on Graduate Work, Graduate Study, Special Committee on the Conduct of Exams.
- Committee Files, 1955, 1956, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  General Committee, Ph.D Major - Minor Sub-committee, Graduate Training Sub-committee
- Committee Files, 1954, 1956, 1963, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Graduate Committee, Registration and Schedules Committee, Faculty Research Grants
- Chairman's Correspondence: Francis Mineka, undated, 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Chairman's Correspondence: Francis Mineka, 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Foreign Students, 1948-1957 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Course Proposals, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Proposals, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Teaching Staff Distributions, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Teaching Staff Distribution, 1948-1957 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Edgar Rosenberg Correspondence and Memos, 1966, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Edgar Rosenberg Correspondence and Memos, 1966, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Statistics, Charts, etc., 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Humanities correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- English Humanities Committee, 1970, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Dorm Courses Spring '71, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Humanities Questionnaire, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Humanities Computer Project (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Six Year Ph.D. Exemptions, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Questionnaire Critiques, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Humanities Project Notes, etc., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- General Problems, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Staff / T.A., 1968, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Course Rating Results, 1968, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Course Rating Results Spring '69, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Spring Term Humanities Courses, 1967, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Requests to T.A.s for Readers, 1968, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- College Scheduling Patterns, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Fall '1969-70 Humanities Courses, 1969, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Fall Term Quotas '69, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Fall '69 Charts, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Fall English Courses, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Interdisciplinary Humanistic Studies Proposal (I.H.S.) (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Social Sciences Course Dowd, Lyons, Condry, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Fall '69 English Staff, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- New Course Ideas, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Spring English, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 69)
- Course Enrollment Figures By College, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Course Preferences In English, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Spring '70 Schedule Pattern, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 72)
- Supply - Demand Statistics, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 73)
- T.A. Course and Hour Preferences, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 74)
- re-Testing OK's, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 75)
- Fall '70 Teaching, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 76)
- Enrollment - Fall, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 77)
- Fall Commitments, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 78)
- Scheduling Patterns, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 79)
- Fall 1970 Ballot and Descriptions, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 80)
- Non-English Courses, Schedules, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 81)
- Faculty Questionnaire (Box 1, Folder 82)
- Student Questionnaire (Box 1, Folder 83)
- Freshman Writing Seminar Brochure and John S. Knight Writing Program Booklet, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 84)
- Class books, with schedules and grades for English Department courses taught by O. F. Emerson. Includes note to Professor White from B.S. Monroe donating them to the library., 1891-1895 (Box 1, Folder 85)